Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is נ"א. nun aleph.
Shhh. 51, we pick up at the bottom of נ' עמוד ב',
nun amud bet, three lines down from the medium-sized lines. Okay, we
had a whole debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel whether there
was the you needed to have הבל hevel in a בור, bore,
this air, this thick air, whatever it was, in order in order
to be חייב, chayav, and the basic difference would be if you
have a little mound and you trip on the mound and you
bang yourself on the ground, so the concern that רב Rav has
his need for הבל hevel is that you need some connection to
the ground that is causing the impact. So in that type of
a case, רב Rav would actually say you would be פטור. patur.
So now the גמרא Gemara says three lines down in the medium-sized
lines on נ' עמוד ב', nun amud bet, תנן: Tnan: היה פחות
מעשרה טפחים. Haya pachot me-asara tefachim.
So we're going to now analyze our משנה mishnah with looking at
this debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. So the משנה mishnah
says if the wells were less than עשרה טפחים asara tefachim ונפל
לתוכו שור או חמור ומת פטור ve-nafal le-tocho shor o chamor u-meit
patur and an ox or donkey fell into it and died, you're
פטור patur if they die because it was not fit to cause
death, ואם הוזק בו חייב v'im huzak bo chayav but if they
were damaged you're חייב. chayav. נפל לתוכו שור
או חמור ומת פטור מאי טעמא? Nafal le-tocho shor o chamor u-meit
patur mai taama?
Why is it that you're פטור patur when they die? לאו משום
דלית ביה חבטותא? Lav mishum d'leisa bei chavatata? It must be that
we are saying because look logically the גמרא Gemara sort of is
also trying to get its head around this idea of הבל. hevel.
So it assumes that the basic difference between how deep it is
is not a difference of הבל, hevel, it's a difference of the
impact, right? There's going to be less of an impact. So you
see, says the גמרא, Gemara, that it is not the הבל hevel
that you're חייב chayav for. Because if you were חייב chayav for
the הבל, hevel, presumably that doesn't change. Okay, and both רב Rav
and שמואל, Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says you're also חייב chayav for the
חבטותא, chavatata, but both רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel say you're חייב
chayav for the הבל. hevel. So the גמרא Gemara says well then
you should be חייב chayav even in a shorter in even in
a shallower בור bore where how is the הבל hevel any different?
It's really just the חבטותא chavatata that's different. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא משום דלית ביה הבלא. Lo mishum d'leisa bei hevla. No,
it's not true, just in the same way there's less חבטותא chavatata
there's less הבלא. hevla. If it's not as deep. אי הכי, Ei
hachi, if that's so, ואם הוזק בו חייב, v'im huzak bo chayav,
why are you חייב chayav if it got damaged? הא לית ביה
הבלא? Ha leisa bei hevla? Like the גמרא Gemara figured for some
reason that הבל hevel was an all or nothing. Impact was more
severe or less severe, enough to cause death, enough to cause injury.
הבל, hevel, it's clear the גמרא Gemara also doesn't exactly know what
הבל hevel is. הבל, hevel, the גמרא Gemara says, okay, either you
don't have it or you have it all. Like if you tell
me you have it then you should be fully חייב. chayav. אמרי:
Amri: אין הבלא למיתה ויש הבלא לניזקין. Ein hevla le-mita ve-yesh hevla
le-nezikin.
There's not enough הבל hevel to cause death, there's enough הבל hevel
to cause damage. Okay, so that's the difference, but it's not a
difference in impact. Now the גמרא Gemara doesn't deny that there's a
difference in impact, but what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that
if you say like רב Rav for example then you need it
always to be הבל hevel is the critical and even according to
שמואל, Shmuel, הבל hevel is a sufficient reason to be חייב. chayav.
So if you're going to be פטור patur for מיתה, mita, you
would have to say there's not enough הבל hevel to cause death.
Okay, yes?
Yes, I mean just yesterday because we raised that
point. But עשרה טפחים asara tefachim is really not that high. I
mean the animal's head if it's a שור shor is above that
angle.
Right.
How does it cause death? I don't know. I mean well the
הבל, hevel, I don't know, I thought you were saying even the
impact. No, the impact too, but how does it cause death?
I don't know. I mean look, they say God forbid, they say
a baby can drown in like an inch of water. So I
don't know. I know, I really have no idea what they. What
bothers me more is that I'd like to believe that this הבל
hevel is not that they really believed it's some mysterious force that
itself could kill, but it is a way of
connecting the person who dug the בור bore to the impact of
the wall. Like I created the הבל, hevel, so therefore it's like
it's my wall, it's like I'm connected to all the damage that
gets created. But it doesn't sound that way in the גמרא Gemara
because then you could acknowledge that there's a difference between the degree
of חבטותא. chavatata. There is a difference between the degree of חבטותא,
chavatata, but the הבל hevel connects you to the חבטותא. chavatata. But
the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to be doing that. The גמרא Gemara
says like no, if you're חייב chayav or פטור patur and if
it's about הבל, hevel, then it all has to be what the
power of the הבל hevel is to do in those circumstances.
Isn't it supposed to be אמות? amot?
No, it's not, I mean but we had that before. Yeah, that
was just one piece. Here there's no question, as we're going to
see anyway in an upcoming story. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ההוא תורא דנפל לאריסתא דדילאי. Hahu tora de-nafal le-arisa de-dilai.
There was an ox
that fell into an irrigation canal which is known to be a
standard
אמה ama deep, okay, which is whatever it is, a foot and
a half, שיתא טפחים, shita tefachim, דדילאי. de-dilai. שחטה מרה, Shechta marei,
so the owner שחטה shechted it before it had a chance to
walk around or whatever, figured I'll שחטה shecht it before it dies
on me. טרפה רב נחמן. Treifa Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said it was a טרפה treifa because even if you don't
see there's this thing called ריסוק אברים, risuk evarim, which is like
the sort of loosening or the of the limbs, which is an
animal suffers an impact even if you don't see any wound or
whatever, there's a concern it will be a טרפה, treifa, it's פסק
paskened to be a טרפה treifa unless it survives a day or
walks around. But if in this case, so you שחטה shechted it
immediately. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this, wait a minute,
right. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, סלקא דעתיה
דרב נחמן, Sal'ka da'ateih de-Rav Nachman,
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, אי שקיל מארי דהאי
תורא כוותא דקמחא, i shekel marei de-hai tura kavta de-kimcha, if the
owner of this ox would have been smart enough to just take
like a measure of flour, ואזיל יתיב בי מדרשא, ve-azil yatib be
midrasha, you know, he had like expended a few bucks and gone
on to take a cab to the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and
learned a little bit and he would have and he could have
learned, what would he have learned? He would have learned, you know,
אם שהתה מעת לעת כשרה, im shas'ta me-es le-es kesheira, if he
would have waited 24 hours it would have been kosher. If he
would have expended a little effort to find out the הלכה, halacha,
then לא אפסיד ליה לתורא, lo afsid lei le-tura, he wouldn't have
lost his ox דשוי כמה כוותא, de-shavei kama kavta, which is worth
many of these measures of flour, worth thousands of dollars. Of course
clearly this guy thought he had to act immediately. If he didn't
act immediately he thought it would die.
Anyway, anyway what's relevant about this? What's relevant is that this whole
גומא guma was only six טפחים tefachim deep. And רב נחמן Rav
Nachman felt that if it felt an impact of six טפחים, tefachim,
that would be enough to create a possibly fatal impact. Okay, now
why is that? It's only six טפחים. tefachim. Our משנה Mishnah says
that a בור bor has to be ten טפחים tefachim to create
a fatal impact. Okay, so אלמא קסבר רב נחמן, alma kasavar Rav
Nachman, you see רב נחמן Rav Nachman is of the opinion, יש
חבטה בפחות מעשרה, yesh chavata be-pachus me-asara, that you can have an
impact less than ten טפחים tefachim deep that could possibly cause death.
איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן, Esivei Rava le-Rav Nachman, so רבא Rava challenged
רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Our משנה, Mishnah, היו פחותים מעשרה טפחים ונפל
לתוכו שור או חמור ומת פטור, hayu p'chusim me-asara tefachim ve-nafal le-socho
shor o chamor va-meis patur,
that you're exempt when it's less than ten טפחים tefachim depth for
death. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? לאו משום דליכא חבטה,
lao mishum de-leika chavata, isn't it because it does not have enough
impact to cause death and therefore how come you טריפת treifed this
animal? So the גמרא Gemara says, top of נ' ע"א, Nun Amud
Aleph, לא משום דליכא הבלא. lo mishum de-leika havla. No, because there's
not enough הבלא. havla. And I therefore, the way רש"י Rashi is,
I פסקן pasken like רב Rav that the חיוב chiyuv is only
for הבלא, havla, so this also, the גמרא Gemara said, even though
the impact is enough to cause death, if it's that shallow, since
the הבלא havla is not enough to cause death, you're not חייב
chayav for בור. bor. Okay, so again, very strange idea. הבלא Havla
is not just to connect you to the impact. We're suggesting that
an impact of a shallow בור bor could cause death, but the
הבלא havla is not enough to create death, and therefore you're going
to be exempt if the animal dies. Okay, so that's exempt from
liability, but here, if the animal actually fell in, it might die.
And that's why רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the animal was a
טרפה. treifa. Yes.
So this case, I'm actually very interested, like you do we don't
are we saying that the animal has to die in the בור
bor or has to die within 24 hours? Let's say it's after
24 hours and dies later. Is he חייב chayav for that or?
You mean by the בור bor case. Yeah, that's a good question.
I mean we sort of had that by the שור shor as
well, קרנא דתורא קבירא ביה, karna de-tura kvira beih, you know.
Yeah, it's an interesting question. I don't know. You're right. I mean
logically I would extend the same logic that we have by the
שור, shor, but maybe not. The שור shor was an active act
of היזק, hezek, this was more passive and whatever, and therefore maybe
more could disconnect the owner from the final death. I don't know.
That's a good question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אי הכי הוזק בחיוב והא ליכא הבלא, ee hachi huzak be-chiyuv ve-ha
leika havla, if you're saying there's no הבלא, havla, why are you
חייב chayav if the animal is damaged? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אין
הבלא למיתה ויש הבלא לנזיקין. ein havla le-misa ve-yesh havla le-nezikin. And
like we said before. But I don't believe the חיוב chiyuv of
a בור bor has anything to do with חבטה, chavata, and the
difference there is about הבלא. havla. But yes, חבטה chavata is enough
to cause death even less than ten טפחים. tefachim. איתיביה, Esivei, I'll
challenge you on this. בית הסקילה הייתה גבוהה שתי קומות. Beis ha-sekila
haysah gvoha shtei komos. The place where they would stone a person
would be two heights
higher than two stories basically. Right, thank you. ואי סלקא
דעתך. ve-ee salka da'atach. Exactly. ותניא עלה, ve-tanya ala, and we taught
another ברייתא braisa on
this, וקומה שלו, ve-koma shelo, and also the height of the actual
person himself. Right, exactly. The person being executed. So basically you have
three heights, you know, the height of three people essentially. Assuming the
קומות, komos, I mean רש"י, Rashi, Michael translated קומות komos as stories,
which is a normal translation, but giving that it says קומה שלו,
koma shelo, I think it might mean three, I think in this
context it means the three people height. Okay, but which is whatever
that is. Okay, so a person so that's like so that's something
like a good ten אמות amos high. All right, 15 feet, ten
אמות amos high, something of that nature. A lot more than ten
טפחים. tefachim. ואי סלקא דעתך, Ve-ee salka da'atach, now he says and
if you think you רב נחמן Rav Nachman that יש חבטה בפחות
מעשרה, yesh chavata be-pachus me-asara, that an impact of less than ten
טפחים tefachim can cause death, like by this animal, למה לי כולי
האי, lama li kulei hai, why do you need it so high?
Of course it's a pretty silly question. It could cause death, but
it will it might be a very slow and painful one and
it won't necessarily cause death. You want to push the guy down
and definitely cause him to die, you want to get it high
enough, you know, that you're pretty certain what the end result will
be. And the גמרא Gemara anyway asks it in a different way.
ולטעמיך, u-le-ta'amich, says the גמרא, Gemara, according to you, נהוי דעשרה, nahavi
de-asara, if okay fine you're trying to challenge me that if less
than ten טפחים tefachim why do you need it so high? Fine.
According to you, ten טפחים tefachim causes death. Why do you need
it so high? This is much higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. אלא.
Ela. To רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* like the other statement,
this is רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*, right? Yeah, like the
other statement of רב נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman*, דאמר *d'amar* רב
Rav. נחמן *Rav Nachman* אמר *amar* רבה בר אבוה *Rabbah bar Abbuha*
אמר *amar* קרא *kra* ואהבת לרעך כמוך *Ve'ahavta Lere'acha Kamocha*, love your
friend neighbor as yourself, ברור לו מיתה misa, יפה *beror lo mita
yafa*, even at the time when you're executing him, he's still your
friend and your neighbor, right? That's a powerful statement. And you should
try to pick a form of execution that you know is one
that you would pick for yourself, right? If something that is painless,
and therefore you want it to be easy. Therefore, within the context
of the הלכה halacha. *Halacha*, and therefore you would want it to
be something that would be like the higher it would be, the
more quick the death would be. Okay, I would also just say
the more certain. Like, you know, ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* can cause
death. You want an execution that will cause death. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says אי הכי *ihachi* נגבה טפי *nagveih tfei*, let's make
it even higher. No, משום דמינוול *mishum deminuvel*, because it will, it
will, like, it will desecrate the body, you know, it'll disfigure the
body. Right, so you know, so you need to have the exact
right balance there. Okay fine. איתיבי *Eitvei*, so we're still trying to
see whether less than ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* is enough of an
impact to cause death. כי יפול הנופל ממנו *Ki yipol hanofel mimenu*,
this is the obligation to create a fence around your roof, lest
a person fall from it. So the ברייתא *braita* says ממנו ולא
לתוכה *mimenu velo betocha*, falls from your roof and not into your
roof. כיצד *Keitzad*, הייתה רשות הרבים reshut harabim, גבוהה ממנו עשרה טפחים
asara tefachim, *hayeta reshut harabim gevoha mimenu asara tefachim*, let's say the
public domain was higher than yours, than your, you know, here you
was, your building was built here.
Right, here's your building. Okay, and your rooftop, and here's the רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim. *reshut harabim*. Okay. An overpass. An overpass. Yeah, that's
a good way of thinking about it. Here's the רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim*. Okay, and here's where you, you know, you are. So somebody's
walking in the רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*, they can fall off the
רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* onto your roof. Now, of course, I'm not
exactly sure what you're going to do there. A fence won't help
much. You might have to like put like, you know, like some
type of a cushion on your roof or something. Anyway, so you're
not obligated. הייתה רשות הרבים גבוהה ממנו עשרה טפחים tefachim ונפל מתוכה
לתוכה *Hayeta reshut harabim gevoha mimenu asara tefachim venafal mitocha letocha*, and
somebody, this doesn't mean fell, this is not a talk of liability,
it means somebody could fall from רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* onto your
roof, פטור patur *patur* you're exempt from building a fence. עמוקה ממנו
עשרה טפחים tefachim *Amuka mimenu asara tefachim*, if the רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim* is ten טפחים tefachim.
*tefachim* below, then you should build a fence for yourself anyway because
you go on the roof you don't want to fall.
That's an interesting point. Why do you have to not prevent yourself
from falling down there? I don't know, it's a good question. Maybe
it's like
built into the ground, so there's no high, I don't know, it's
a really good question.
Maybe your rooftop is very short, maybe you're like a Hobbit place
or something and then I don't know. That's a good question. Anyway,
I don't know, I mean, the bottom line is I don't know
why it's just focusing on רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*, especially when it's
talking about you falling. Who cares where you fall? You're falling off
the roof. You don't care if you fall in רשות
הרבים *reshut harabim*. הייתה, where was I? Okay. עמוקה ממנו עשרה טפחים
tefachim ונפל מתוכה לתוכה *Amuka mimenu asara tefachim venafal mitocha letocha*, if
the רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* is ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* below the
ground is ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* below your rooftop, ונפל מתוכה לתוכה
*venafal mitocha letocha* and you could fall from your rooftop onto the
ground, חייב chayav *chayav*. Okay, so basically you're חייב chayav *chayav* if
there is a ten טפח tefach *tefach* height to fall from. So
why do you need a ten טפח tefach *tefach* height to fall
from? Presumably because less than that will not, doesn't have the possibility
of causing death. And presumably you don't need a fence if you
don't have a potentially fatal fall, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואי סלקא דעתך דאית חבטה chavata בפחות
מעשרה *ve'isalka daatach de'ish chavata bepachot mei'asara*, but if you think that
you can have an impact less than ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* that
cause, that could actually cause death, למה לי עשרה *lama li asara*?
Why do you need your rooftop be ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* off
the ground? Even less than ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* off the ground.
אמר ליה amar leih: *Amar lei*, he said back to him, שאני
בית דכל פחות מעשרה לאו בית הוא *shani bayit dekol pachot mei'asara
lav bayit hu*. You know what, you're right. You don't need ten
טפחים tefachim *tefachim* in order to create a big enough fall. You
need ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* in order to define something as a
בית *bayit*. Okay? You're only חייב chayav *chayav* to build a fence
on your בית *bayit*. If you own something that הלכתית *halachically* doesn't
have the status of a בית *bayit*, even though it could cause
exactly this type of an injury, you are exempt technically from building
a מעקה *ma'akeh*, a fence. So yes, it could have a big
enough impact, but it's not a בית *bayit*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says one minute, אי הכי התם נמי דהוי מעברא עשרה *ihachi
hatam nami dehavi me'abara asara*, so what, if the issue is that
you need something to be ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* to be a
בית *bayit*, presumably we mean ten טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* of the inside,
of the inner cavity. So if that's true, why is ten טפחים
tefachim *tefachim* fall enough to make something a בית *bayit*? Ten טפחים
tefachim. *tefachim* fall is measured from the outside. Okay? So השתא נמי
דהוי מעברא עשרה *hashta nami dehavi me'abara asara*, even if it's from
the outside measured as ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, דלי deli תקרה ומעזיבה
*dalei tikra ve'aziva*, if you subtract the thickness of the rooftop and
the plaster, מגואי לא הוי עשרה *migavai lo havei asara*, on the
inside it won't be ten on the inside. So if the real
issue of ten is not the degree of the fall but the
definition of a house, presumably that's because you need a cavity of
ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, a height of ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* inside
in order to be considered living space. If that's true, if we
have a technical need for בית *bayit*, how does ten טפחים tefachim.
*tefachim* on the outside satisfy that? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said back to him, כגון kegon דדחק
מגואי *kegon dedachak migavai*. Okay, so it's ten טפחים tefachim on the
outside, but it's also ten טפחים tefachim on the inside. How? Because
you dug into the ground,
so you actually have a lower floor than the floor outside the
house. יכי yachi says the גמרא, Gemara if that's the scenario we're
talking about, that it's a house because you've dug on the inside,
then we're back to it could be less than ten טפחים tefachim.
on the outside. כי לא הוי נמי מבירא עשרה ומשכחת לה. ki
lo havei nami mibeira asara umishkachat lah. You could also have a
house that's less than ten, that's fewer than ten, less than ten
טפחים tefachim height on the outside. דהוי מגואי עשרה. dehavei migavai asara.
And on the inside it will be ten. כגון דחקק בטפי. kigon
dechachak bitfei. You have a very big, you know,
hole that you dug on the inside, so measured on the inside
it's ten טפחים tfachim. from the floor to the ceiling, to the
bottom of the ceiling, measured on the outside it's less than ten
טפחים. tefachim. So we're back to the point that don't give me
this answer about that we're defining a house. Clearly what we're defining
is the fall. And less than ten טפחים tefachim. is not a
fall that causes death, which is again פשט pshat in our משנה.
Mishnah. So how did רב נחמן make this animal a טריפה? treifah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, fine, you got me. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
אלא היינו טעמא דרב נחמן. ela hainu ta'ama deRav Nachman. Here's רב
נחמן's reasoning. Not because less than ten can cause a fatal injury.
That's true, it cannot. You need ten to cause a fatal injury.
But here's his reasoning.
סבר מכריסא דתורא לארעא כמה הוי. savar michreisa detora leara kama havei.
From the underside of an ox's belly to the ground, what's the
height?
ארבע. arba. Four טפחים. tefachim I don't know if you've ever measured
it. But okay, that's what it
is. Four טפחים. tefachim. ורישא דדילאי כמה הוי. urisha dedilai kama havei.
The depth of this irrigation canal how much is it? שיתא. shita.
Six טפחים. tefachim הא עשרה. ha asara. So it fell ten טפחים.
tefachim. Okay? So, you got it?
Here's your cow. Now I get to draw a cow. Here's your
cow. That's four טפחים tefachim to the ground. Okay? And then it
fell six טפחים tefachim down into there. So the impact, right? I
mean it could have, maybe it died by impact by killing its
head. But anyway, the impact was ten טפחים. tefachim Okay? Of course,
you have to like imagine, I guess, I don't know how it
fell. I mean I guess if it fell by tipping over, right?
That also would be a ten טפחים tefachim
fall. Okay? That also would
be ten טפחים, tefachim right? I mean I always, you know, it's
not like it's like splayed out and a splat, but it fell
over, then this also is going to be a ten טפחים tefachim
fall. Okay? אישתכח דכי קא מחבט, ishtakach dechi ka machbat, you see
that when
it gets the impact,
מעשרה דקא מחבט, me'asara deka machbat, it's getting an impact of ten
טפחים. tefachim. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מתניתין דקתני בבור שיש
בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים אף כל שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה
טפחים. ela matnitin deka tani bebor sheyesh bo kedei lehamit asara tefachim
af kol sheyesh bo kedei lehamit asara tefachim. בשיתא נמי סגי. beshita
nami sagi. Six טפחים tefachim would be enough for animals if we
assume that this is the general height of the animals off the
ground. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמי מתניתין דאיגנדר לבור. ami matnitin
de'igandar lebor.
You're right. Our משנה Mishnah is that it rolled into the בור.
bor. Okay, the animal was like rolling in the dirt and then
it had to be ten טפחים tefachim deep. But if the actual
animal fell from a standing position into the בור, bor, you'd be
חייב chayav even less than ten טפחים tefachim. deep, which is of
course not at all פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah but anything
we've ever said. Now we find out that in most normal cases
the בור bor doesn't have to be ten טפחים. tefachim, At least
it has to be six, at least according to רב נחמן.
And even with that you have like this bad air?
Yeah, what can I tell you? That's a good question. Then you
have to say the הבל hevel is in less than ten טפחים
tefachim according to רב. I don't know what to say about any
of this. Let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah. בור של שני
שותפין. bor shel shenei shutafin. Okay, you have a well that's owned
or a pit that's owned by two people. עבר עליו הראשון ולא
כיסהו. avar alav harishon velo chisahu. The first one passed by and
didn't cover it. והשני ולא כיסהו. vehasheni velo chisahu. And the second
did not cover it. השני חייב. hasheni chayav. Which is interesting. Why
don't you say the first one was also negligent? If you look
at the side it says, גרסת הרי"ף והרמב"ם הראשון חייב. girsa deharif
veharambam harishon chayav. So that's going to be muddy, the core question
of what is the ruling here? Right, there's three possibilities. Both, which
is clearly not the פסק psak of the משנה, Mishnah, or the
first guy or the last guy. But there's a question of what
the גירסא girsa is. So we will wait a while till we
get to that, which is the core point of the משנה, Mishnah,
and let's first see what the concern of the גמרא Gemara is.
אמי, ami, the גמרא Gemara says, בור של שני שותפין היכי משכחת
לה. bor shel shenei shutafin heichi mishkachat lah. How do you get
a well owned by two people? הניחא למאן דאמר כרבי עקיבא haniicha
leman de'amar keRabbi Akiva דאמר בור ברשותו חייב de'amar bor birshuto chayav
that one of the obligations of a בור bor is if you
own it,
it comes through ownership, not through digging. So משכחת לה בחצר של
שניהם בבור של שניהם. mishkachat lah bechatzer shel sheneihem bebor shel sheneihem.
That basically two people owned a field
in partnership together with the pit in the field. והפקירו רשותן ולא
הפקירו את בורן. vehipkiru reshutan velo hipkiru et boran.
And they renounced ownership of the yard but not of the well,
so they remained property owners, like title owners, joint title owners of
the well. That's an easy scenario. ואי סבירא לן בור ברשותו פטור,
ve'i sevira lan bor birshuto patur, but if you're never liable for
case of ownership and you're only liable for case of... actual digging
of the well, so היכא משכחת לה דחייב ליה? heicha mashkachat lah
d'chayav leh? היכא משכחת לה דחייב ליה, heicha mashkachat lah d'chayav leh,
when are you חייב chayav for a בור ברשות הרבים? bor b'reshut
harabim? If you dig it in the public domain where you're not
dealing with a real property title ownership, ברשות הרבים, b'reshut harabim, בור
של שני שותפין היכא משכחת לה? bor shel shnei shutafin heicha mashkachat
lah? How do you get two people to be equally liable for
digging the well? Okay, אי דשוו שליח תרוייהו, ei d'shavvu shliach taryaihu,
let's say they both, you know, appointed a third person to say
אמר להו זילו כרו לי, amar lehu zilu kuru li, go dig
for us a well there in the רשות הרבים, okay, they hired
somebody to do it. So then when he did it, it's like
both of them did it. ואזל כרה להו, v'azal karah lehu, and
he goes and he digs it. אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shliach
l'dvar aveira. You can't make a שליח shliach to do a sin.
Now, the normally that's used to say that like in terms of
like some punishment by בית דין Beit Din or something, you know,
not a civil liability. But here the גמרא Gemara so you can
go two ways. You can say the גמרא Gemara is actually saying
that you do עבירה aveira by making a בור ברשות הרבים, bor
b'reshut harabim, which actually is an interesting question that we have never
addressed because the גמרא Gemara doesn't directly address, which is: what do
you transgress besides the question of civil liability? Do you transgress anything
by making these נזקין? nezikin? You know, by I mean there's different
degrees. There's making a בור ברשות הרבים, bor b'reshut harabim, there's not
just that's an active thing, an active thing on your account, like
the person gets damaged more passively. There's not being negligent watching your
ox, that's more passive on your account. Are you doing any type
of an עבירה aveira by creating potential hazards, you know, for the
רבים? rabim? So the בור ברשות הרבים bor b'reshut harabim actually a
number of ראשונים Rishonim say, oh yeah, there's a פסוק pasuk about
that, which is לפני עור לא תתן מכשול. lifnei iver lo titein
michshol. So we normally translate that metaphorically, but there is like a
literal meaning of that. Now you could say people aren't necessarily blind,
but nevertheless you're really creating a מכשול michshol for people. Okay, so
it is possible to say, yeah, there really is an עבירה, aveira,
but nevertheless nobody says the liability of a בור bor is because
of the sin of the בור. bor. So normally so this is
probably best understood to be a little bit more sort of used
more figuratively and saying the same way you don't have to get
punished in שמים Shamayim or in בית דין Beit Din for somebody
else's sin, you're not going to have civil liability for somebody else's
actions. That person is still choosing to listen to you, he dug
the well, he's responsible for his actions, you're not responsible for his
actions.
Okay, if a company sends me on a construction project, you know,
to dig a בור, bor, I'm liable, not the company.
According to, yeah, הלכה. halacha I mean it'd be an interesting question
if you're like an אונס ones because you sort of like trust
the company or something like that, you know, that they were telling
you to go in a place that you were legally entitled to
go, right, be an interesting question about what would be if you
have a type of an אונס ממון ones mamon in that regard,
like if you're afraid of losing your job, right, so in a
sense, you know, they're holding that sort of threat over you, right,
would that sort of I don't know, those are interesting questions. But
in principle the answer is yes.
Okay, ואי דכרה האי חמשה והאי חמשה, v'ei d'karah hai chamisha v'hai
chamisha, if Reuben dug five טפחים tefachim. and Shimon dug five טפחים.
tefachim נסתלקו מעשה ראשון. nistalku maaseh rishon. We're going to see in
a minute that when the second guy does it and turns it
into a full בור bor because a full בור bor is עשרה
טפחים, then he takes ownership over the whole בור. bor. It's considered
fully his בור bor since he made it from less than ten
to ten. Okay, now this is going to actually be a little
bit of a debate. הניחא לרבי, hani'cha l'Rabbi, this will be good
according to רבי, Rabbi, which we'll see momentarily, ולנזיקין, u'l'nezikin, because רבי
Rabbi will say even though the second guy turned it into a
בור bor that can kill and the second guy is liable for
death, right, they're both equally liable for damage. So for רבי Rabbi
you can get a בור bor of שני שותפין shnei shutafin if
they both dig five, that even though one is responsible for death,
they're both responsible for damage, that would be a scenario where they're
both equally responsible each for damage.
משכחת לה. mashkachat lah. אלא לרבי ולמיתה, ela l'Rabbi u'l'mita, but for
רבי Rabbi to be liable jointly liable for the death of an
animal, ולרבנן בין למיתה בין לנזיקין, u'l'rabbanan bein l'mita bein l'nezikin, for
the Rabbis whether death or damages, היכא משכחת לה? heicha mashkachat lah?
You won't find it. Because when the second guy does it, for
רבי Rabbi he's the only one liable for death and for the
Rabbis he's the only one liable for death or damages. So when
are you going to what what would be the scenario? So we'll
see the גמרא's Gemara answer and then we can imagine a lot
of other answers too. So אמר רב יוחנן כגון שעקרו שם חיוב
בבת אחת והשלימו לעשרה. amar Rav Yochanan k'gon she'akru shem chiyuv b'vat
achat v'hishlimu l'asara. Okay, so they you know they took turns digging
it and they got it down to nine and a half טפחים
and then there was that one little it's sort of like that
christening event, you know, when you have they both wanted to own
this as the בור bor that they were going to be חייב
chayav. on so they both jointly pulled out that last half inch
and then they both made it into a בור של עשרה. bor
shel asara. Okay, so now what I don't get is why you
couldn't imagine a case where like you know what would happen if
like you know this guy is digging here and this guy is
digging here, right, and it's a very wide בור, bor, they're each
sort of digging in their own holes, right, and then it gets
combined and it's one בור, bor, right, that would be a case
where they would both have dug the full depth? Anyway, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
This for damages? What? This for damages?
If they're jointly negligent? So we're going to yeah they would split
the question is what happens if only one of them is around
and not the other, but if they're both around then yes then
they do split damages. Right. So the גמרא Gemara says
in this case yeah okay so let's say the גמרא Gemara, says
okay. מאי רבי ומאי רבנן? Mai Rabbi u-mai Rabbanan? What's the debate
of רבי Rabbi and the רבנן? Rabbanan? תניא. Tanya. אחד החופר בור
תשעה, Echad hachofer bor tisha, one guy digs it nine, and בא
אחר והשלימו לעשרה, ba acher vehishlimo le-asara, and the other guy went
and made the ten. האחרון חייב. Ha-acharon chayav. The last guy is
liable for everything. He turned it from a not really a full
בור bor into a full בור. bor. רבי אומר. Rabbi omer. אחר
אחרון למיתה. achar acharon le-misa. No, the last guy is fully liable
for its ability for any death that occurs in the well. ואחר
שניהם לנזיקין. ve-acher shneihem le-nezikin. But they're both liable for damages because
they both created a בור bor of damages. It was a בור
bor that could damage before it reached ten. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai
ta'ama de-Rabbanan? What's the reason of the Rabbis? דאמר קרא. De-amar kra.
The verse says כי יפתח וכי יכרה. ki yiftach ve-chi yichre. If
a person opens or digs a well. אם על פתיחה חייב על
כריה לא כל שכן. im al psicha chayav al kriya lo kol
she-kein. If you're חייב chayav. for opening, certainly you're חייב chayav for
digging. אלא להביא כורה אחר כורה. Ela le-havi kore acher kore. שסילק
מעשה ראשון. she-silak ma'aseh rishon. It's coming to tell you that the
guy who digs after the guy who digs, like the extra word
of כי יכרה ki yichre is to tell you that if you
do an additional digging, you could be fully חייב. chayav. Okay, that
if you remove the meaningfulness of the previous guy's act. Meaning, if
he dug five, if he dug three and you dug three, you're
both חייב. chayav. But if you did something that really transformed the
בור, bor, he made it less than ten and you made it
into ten, then it's all your בור. bor. Okay, so ורבי אמר
לך. ve-Rabbi amar lach. הנהו מצריך צריכי. hanehu mitzrach tzrichi. No, you
need both of those phrases. כדאמרן. kiddamran. Like we said. Remember, like
you need to tell me you're חייב chayav if all you do
is open it, that that's not trivial. You also have to tell
me that if you dig it, you're פטור pattur. as long as
you cover it, you don't have to refill it. So it's not
a problem. רבי Rabbi says there's no redundancy in the פסוק. pasuk.
ורבנן נמי מצריך צריכי. Ve-Rabbanan nami mitzrach tzrichi. The Rabbis would concede
that it needs to talk about both scenarios. ואלא היינו טעמא דרבנן.
Ve-ela hainu ta'ama de-Rabbanan. And this is the reason of the Rabbis
to say that the last guy becomes fully liable. אמר קרא. Amar
kra. כי יכרה איש בור. ki yichre ish bor. A man. ולא
שנים. ve-lo shnayim. Not two. Okay, now of course you don't need
that when literally only one of them does it, but it means
that there'll be cases where two people will do it but one
is really seen as the primary person. And they understand that this
is the case when he transforms it into ten
טפחים. ורבי ve-Rabbi would say. ההוא מיבעי ליה. hahu miba'ei lei. כי
יכרה איש בור ולא שור בור. ki yichre ish bor ve-lo shor
bor. If a man digs and not an ox digs. If an
ox digs your well, you are not liable for it.
ולא שור בור. ve-lo shor bor. ורבנן. ve-Rabbanan. תרי איש בור כתיבי.
trei ish bor ktivi. It says it twice. כי יפתח איש בור
כי יכרה איש בור. ki yiftach ish bor ki yichre ish bor.
It says איש ish twice. החד לומר. ha-chad lomar. That the one
is to tell you that there'll be times when only one person
is liable even though both dug. ורבי ve-Rabbi and רבי Rabbi would
say. איידי דכתב הא כתב הא. aidi de-katav ha katav ha. No,
it says איש ish one time which it had to say, it
said it the other time, but it's not to tell you anything
new. וממאי דלחיובא דבתרא. u-mimai de-lechiyuva de-basra. Now the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so the Rabbis have איש בור. ish bor. So that tells
me that there are times two people do it and only one
is חייב. chayav Who told you it's the last guy that did
it? דילמא לחיובא דקמא. dilma le-chiyuva de-kama. Maybe it's the first guy.
לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka dach-tach. That doesn't make sense. דאמר קרא.
de-amar kra. והמת יהיה לו. ve-ha-mes yiheyeh lo. And the carcass will
be his. ההוא דקעביד מיתה. hahu de-ka-avid misa. The one who becomes
fully liable is the one who turned it into a בור bor
that has the ability for death. That's the guy that transformed it.
We're talking about a case that the animal died. That's the one
that's fully liable. והא והמת יהיה לו מיבעי ליה לכדרבא. Ve-ha ve-ha-mes
yiheyeh lo miba'ei lei le-chide-Rava. One minute, you need that to tell
me a teaching of רבא. Rava. ודאמר רבא. u-de-amar Rava. רבא Rava
teaches. שור פסולי המוקדשים שנפל לבור פטור. shor psulei ha-mukdashim she-nafal le-bor
patur. If you have an ox that was used to be a
קרבן korban and is not a קרבן. korban. I sanctified my ox
as a קרבן korban and then it got a מום mum and
then I redeemed it. So the הלכה halacha? is what can I
do with this ox? Now that it's been redeemed, but it used
to be a קרבן. korban. I can שחט shacht it, I can
eat the meat, I can't work it, but I can שחט shacht
it and I can eat the meat. I can get benefits. But
one of the הלכות halachos also is is that if it dies
and becomes a נבלה, neveila, I cannot use it as dog food.
I can't get any benefit out of it as a carcass if
it wasn't שחט-ed. shacht So והמת יהיה לו ve-ha-mes yiheyeh lo means
a case where the carcass is usable by the owner. But if
it is a case of this bizarre case of a שור פסולי
המוקדשים shor psulei ha-mukdashim where the carcass is not usable, then you
have no liability. The owner, it's not like you caused him a
loss. He could have שחט-ed shacht the animal and got a thousand
dollars worth of meat out of it. But nevertheless, it's an arbitrary
exemption that you are not liable in a case like this where
the carcass is something that the owner cannot derive benefit from.
Okay, so והמת יהיה לו שנאמר והמת יהיה לו במי שהמת שלו.
ve-ha-mes yiheyeh lo she-ne'emar ve-ha-mes yiheyeh lo be-mi she-ha-mes shelo. So if
that's what you learn from it, not this idea of the second
guy who digs the well. אמרי Amri you can say. הלא מינה
שמעת מינה דבהו דעביד מיתה קאזלינן. halo minei shamas mina de-behu de-avid
misa kazlinan. Fine, that's the case we're learning this way of exempting
this type of an ox of liability for this type of an
ox, but it tells you that we're talking about a scenario where
you dug the well so that it could kill. And therefore, in
a scenario where the well was done so it could kill, then
the person who got it to that stage is the one who's
חייב. chayav Okay, so that's the debate of רבי Rabbi and the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Everybody agrees that you're חייב chayav for the death if
you made it, if you gave it that ability. The question is
have you completely transformed it and are you now חייב chayav for
everything? Now תוספות Tosafot points out that there are even scenarios where
the רבי Rabbi and the רבנן Rabbanan that both could be חייב
chayav, without this case of pulling out the last thing. Here's a
case that they're both חייב chayav for נזיקין. nezikin. You dug three
and I dug three. We're both חייב chayav for נזיקין nezikin according
to everybody. Right? The The רבנן Rabbanan. *Rabbanan* only say things change
because I qualitatively changed its identity. Here’s a way we’re both חייב
chayav *chayiv* for מיתה *misa*. You dug ten and I made it
and I dug another ten. So you made it to have the
ability or I made it. I didn’t transform it qualitatively, okay? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so תוספות *Tosafot* says there really are
scenarios where they could both easily both be חייב chayav *chayiv*, but
the גמרא *Gemara* was dealing with a standard בור bor *bor* which
is assumed to be ten טפחים *tefachim*. So if it’s exactly ten
טפחים *tefachim*, how could they both dig it and both be חייב
chayav? *chayiv*? Okay, and that’s why it speaks about them pulling that
last piece and ground out together.
Okay, תנו רבנן Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*, three lines from the bottom. אחד
חופר בור bor עשרה ובא חברו והשלימו לעשרים ובא חברו והשלימו לשלושים
*Echad chover bor asara uba chavero v’hishlimo l’esrim uba chavero v’hishlimo l’shloshim*
so here’s that scenario, one guy digs ten, the other gets it
to twenty, the other guy gets it to thirty. כולן חייבין *Kulan
chayavin*. They’re all equally liable even according to the רבנן Rabbanan, *Rabbanan*
because everybody made it a בור bor. מיתה *bor misa*. Now, of
course the question would be let’s say one guy digs it look
at this little תוספות *Tosafot*. בור bor י ובא חברו והשלימו לעשרים
*Bor yud uba chavero v’hishlimo l’esrim* תוספות *Tosafot* says הוא הדין אף
ליוד אלף למאי דפחא ליה מסיא וכייא *hu hadin af l’yud aleph
l’mai d’parcha l’mei siya v’kiyay*. Now that’s a little bit of a
shocker, right? I dug it ten and you made it eleven. So
you could say I’m the only one חייב chayav, *chayiv* for מיתה
*misa*. I dug a שיעור מיתה *shiur misa*, you didn’t. Or you
could say once it has the potential to kill and I you
added another טפח tefach *tefach*, you made it more lethal, right? On
the other hand, what, you know, your extra טפח tefach *tefach* makes
you just as liable as my first ten טפחים *tefachim*? So that’s
an interesting quest- the גמרא *Gemara* gives an easy case. I dug
ten and you dug ten, right? But what if I dug ten
and you dug one? Anyway, so תוספות *Tosafot* says it would be
the same. Okay, ורמיה ליה *u-remiya lei* ask you from the ברייתא
*beraita*. אחד חופר בור bor עשרה ובא חברו וסיידו וכיידו *Echad chover
bor asara uba chavero v’siyado v’kiyado*, one person dug ten and the
other person came plastered and like, you know, engraved, the engraving isn’t
really just thrown in, okay? האחרון חייב chayav. *He-acharon chayiv*. The last
guy. Now that why is that? That’s a bizarre. The first guy
dug ten, so that presumably makes it sound more than we’ve said
before, the last person, not just the person who made it into
a ten טפח tefach. *tefach* בור bor, *bor*. The last person who
did something of significance takes over ownership of the בור bor *bor*,
is seen as now it’s your בור bor, *bor*, you went you
changed it, it’s now yours. So the גמרא *Gemara* says...
right, so that’s the way רש״י Rashi *Rashi* reads it.
Right, so רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says, right, thank you, שמתחילה רחבו לא
היה בו הבל hevel כל כך וזה סיידו וכיידו *She-mitichila rechavo lo
haya bo hevel kol kach v’zeh siyado v’kiyado*. רש״י Rashi. *Rashi* says
it’s not just something trivial. You actually transformed it into Now I
would have said because I’m obviously more inclined to think about חבטה
chavata. *chavata* that you made it harder and you made a harder
impact of the בור bor *bor*. Okay, and this is actually a
case where it’s not קרקע עולם *karka olam*. You added the plaster.
Right, but רש״י *Rashi* at least focusing on the הבל hevel, *hevel*
says you also made the הבל hevel. *hevel* more lethal. Okay, so
how do you explain this? You know, that the last guy- so
לימא *leima* let’s say הא רבי Rabbi הא רבנן Rabbanan? *ha Rebbi
ha Rabbanan*
that the one that says everybody is חייב chayav *chayiv* is רבי
Rabbi *Rebbi* who’s more willing to distribute and the one that says
it’s the last guy is the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* that says when
you make it into ten you’re חייב chayav. *chayiv*, so maybe even
if it’s already ten, maybe the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* could say that
you’re חייב chayav. *chayiv*, okay, right, that’s the last guy, meaning even
if it started as a full בור bor. *bor* of ten, maybe
the last guy takes over as the ownership. So the גמרא *Gemara*
said, אמר רב זביד *amar Rav Zvid* no הא והא רבנן *ha
v’ha Rabbanan* it’s both according to the רבנן *Rabbanan*. עד כאן לא
קאמרי רבנן אחרון חייב chayav. *Ad kan lo kamreih Rabbanan acharon chayiv*
now we clarify exactly what we’ve been saying. When do the rabbis
say the last guy takes it over? אלא היכא דלא עבד קמא
שיעור מיתה *Ella heicha d’lo avid kama shiur misa* when the first
guy had not yet made it lethal and then the second guy
made it lethal, he completely transformed it. אלא היכא דעבד קמא שיעור
מיתה *Ella heicha d’avid kama shiur misa* when the first guy made
it lethal, אפילו רבנן מודו דכולם חייבין *afilu Rabbanan modu d’kulan chayavin*
then the rabbis agree that you never that, you know, you never
lose the first person’s acts. He made it lethal, you could have
made it more lethal, but you don’t you know, the first person
remains חייב chayav. *chayiv*. Okay, so then what’s the explanation of the
second ברייתא *beraita*? הא וסיידו וכיידו *ha siyado v’kiyado* how about this
idea of סיידו וכיידו *siyado v’kiyado*? דקא עבד קמא שיעור מיתה וקתני
אחרון חייב chayav, *D’ka avid kama shiur misa v’katani acharon chayiv* how
are you going to explain the second ברייתא *beraita* that the first
guy did ten טפחים *tefachim* and it was lethal and then we’re
getting the second guy to be fully חייב chayav, *chayiv* because he
added the plaster?
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמרי התם שלא היה בו הבל hevel.
למיתה ובא אחר והוסיף בו הבל hevel למיתה *amri hasham she-lo haya
bo hevel l’misa uba acher v’hosif bo hevel l’misa*. So this would
follow רב *Rav* that would say you need הבל hevel. *hevel* and
this is like Hillel was saying or I’ve been quoting earlier רש״י
*Rashi*. Yes, it was ten טפחים *tefachim* deep. It had enough to
create an impact of מיתה *misa* but it did not have enough
הבל hevel *hevel*. תוספות *Tosafot* basically says that although the גמרא *Gemara*
said before that even different types of dimensions of a בור bor.
*bor* have הבל hevel. *hevel*, but if it is wider than it
is deep, then it wouldn’t have הבל hevel *hevel*. And this person
so added some thickness to the wall to make it narrow enough
that it would have הבל hevel *hevel*. Okay, and that’s why he’s
חייב chayav. *chayiv*. But it would be like a case of nine
and ten. Okay. וקתני דקא עבד קמא שיעור מיתה וקתני *v’katani d’ka
avid kama shiur misa v’katani* okay ובא אחר והוסיף בו הבל hevel,
למיתה
*v’hosif bo hevel l’misa*. Alright, so that’s an answer which is not
super satisfying but whatever that’s the answer. איכא דאמרי ika de-amri, *Ika
d’amri* some say אמר רב זביד *amar Rav Zvid* הא והא רבי
Rabbi, *ha v’ha Rebbi* it’s both רבי Rabbi *Rebbi* that normally says
you that really is inclined to equally distribute the the obligation. הכי
קתני כולן חייבין *Hach d’katani kulan chayavin* the guy at ten and
twenty and thirty they’re all חייב chayav, *chayiv*. שפיר *Shappir* that makes
sense. הא דקתני אחרון חייב *Ha d’katani acharon chayiv* The one that
it says it's the last guy with the
דקייד, כגון שלא היה בהבל shelo haya bahevel לא למיתה ולא לנזיקין,
lo l'misa v'lo l'nezikin, similar type of an answer. It was so
wide that it had no effective הבל hevel to cause any liability.
So the first guy did nothing. Okay? I mean you could imagine
that, you could imagine if you dig a deep thing, I mean
I wouldn't say, I wouldn't say base it on the הבל, hevel,
but I would have said that if you have like a sloping
incline, that you could imagine digging something deep, you know, that as
long as you have enough of a gradual slope, it's not a
hazard. And then somebody else comes and plasters but I'm thinking about
חבטה not about הבל. hevel Anyway, ובא אחר והוסיף בה הבל בין
למיתה בין לנזיקין. u'va acher v'hosif ba hevel bein l'misa bein l'nezikin.
What?
A swimming pool is like that. It goes gradually to the deep.
Ah, that's a good point, right right. Okay, so anyway, so what
we're trying to do is we're trying to turn this into a
case where the first guy did not, even though he dug a
ten, didn't do anything significant enough and that's why it allows the
second guy to be totally חייב, okay, whether you explain it according
to רבי Rabbi or according to or according to the רבנן. Okay,
אמר רבא Amar Rava הניח אבן על פי הבור והשלימה לעשרה באנו
למחלוקת רבי ורבנן. hiniach even al pi habor v'hishlima l'asara, banu l'machlokes
Rabbi v'Rabbanan. Let's say one guy dug a בור bor of nine
טפחים.
Okay, here's, I don't know why I made it so small,
because it was only nine טפחים. Okay, here's nine טפחים and then
you came and you put a stone right by, here, here's the
רשות הרבים. Why am I having a hard time here drawing three-dimensional?
I don't know. Anyway, okay, here's this. Okay,
here's the, I guess it's a cut, whatever. Anyway, okay, and then
anyway you came and you put a stone right here. Okay? So
then the person that's now going to trip, he's going to walk,
he's going to trip over it and now he's going to fall
a total of ten טפחים. Okay? So that's what you did. You
made it now, but of course that extra טפח tefach you didn't,
it didn't give it an extra טפח tefach, of הבל. hevel. So
if you're a הבל hevel person, you know, you're not going to
be happy with this. You're not enough to be חייב because it
only has nine טפחים of הבל. hevel. Okay? So, okay, so הניח
אבן על פי הבור והשלימה לעשרה hiniach even al pi habor v'hishlima
l'asara and you got it up to ten טפחים.
באנו למחלוקת רבי ורבנן. banu l'machlokes Rabbi v'Rabbanan. That's the debate of
רבי Rabbi and רבנן. By ignoring the הבל hevel issue I just
said. It was a nine טפח tefach. בור bor. that became a
ten טפח tefakh. בור. bor. So according to רבי, according to, everybody
says only the last guy is חייב for מיתה, but according to
רבי they're both חייב for נזק nezek and the rabbis say only
the last guy is חייב for נזק. nezek. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, it's
a case of nine and ten. No. מהו דתימא למטה הוא דהב
לדידיה קקטיל ליה אבל למעלה דלא הב לדידיה קקטיל ליה אימא לא
קמשמע לן. mahu d'teima lemata hu dehav l'didei k'katil lei aval l'ma'ala
d'lo hav l'didei k'katil lei eima lo kamashma lan. I might have
thought that when is it that you say the last guy is
חייב? When you dig at the depth of the tenth טפח. tefakh.
Because then it's like you created that last טפח Tefakh. of הבל.
And
therefore according to, who's this, and therefore according to the רבנן, you're
going to be fully חייב, okay, because you actually created it. But
here, even if we say that nine טפחים of הבל is enough
to kill someone, or I don't know how, but he's dying in
the הבל of the first guy. Okay. So is this רבי or
the רבנן?
What? Both רבי and the רבנן that no matter what you'll be
פטור.
pattur No, well you could have said that. You could have said
that the last guy was פטור patur because maybe it's not just
enough that I created a, I mean what we're saying is what
makes that last guy the full owner? So here's a case where
the last guy made the בור bor. fully lethal, okay, but the
part of the בור bor. that's killing, forget the הבל, הבל is
confusing. Let's think about it in terms of חבטה. If I dig
the last טפח, tefakh you died on, okay somebody I guess could
hit themselves against the wall, but if they hit themselves or the
animal hit itself on the floor, it died on the floor that
I exposed. So not only did I make it lethal, I created,
ultimately, I exposed that last piece that was the piece that created,
that was the impact. So then it's easy to say it's all
my בור, bor. which is what the רבנן say. But in this
case, I made it more lethal, but the person impacted on the
בור bor created by the first guy. So it's actually you hear
the סברא. sevara. If you get rid of the הבל, which is
confusing, you hear the סברא sevara that the ownership here is not
as much for the last guy as when the last guy creates,
does the last טפח. tefakh. Okay? אימא לא
קמשמע לן. eima lo kamashma lan. Fine. Okay. בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava.
Now רבא Rava asks. טם טפח וסילק אבניו מהו. Tam tefach v'sillek
avnav mahu. Let's say a person basically like sealed up the בור,
the well, okay, and then he removed his stone, like he filled
it up with stones or whatever, and then he took his stones
away. Okay? So whose בור is it?
חנן Chanan digs a well. I decide to do a public service
and I fill up the well and then I say, you know
what, I actually need those rocks, or and then I undig it.
Okay? So what do you say? מי אמרינן מאי דעבד שקליה? Mi
amrinan mai d'avad shaklei? I just neutralized whatever I did before and
it goes back to being חנן's Chanan well. או דילמא כיון דאסתתם
אסתלק מעשה ראשון? O dilma keivan d'istatam istallek ma'aseh rishon? No, as
soon as it got filled up, it stopped being חנן's Chanan well.
And now I remove my, my, my stones, right? If... Dirt, it's
more obvious because I really have transformed the ground. But if it's
stones, it's his well filled with stones. So do we say even
as his well filled with stones, it stops being his well, it's
now and then I remove it, I've now made a well.
Okay, or or a hole. וקמלי כולה ברשותיה, V'kamli kulei b'rishusei, now
it's all mine. תיקו. Teiku. So that's a really good question. I
assume as I said if we if I filled it with dirt
and redug it, it would definitely be my well. But if I
filled it with stones and then removed the stones, that's a more
interesting question. Does it go back to being his and he's liable,
right? Now of course you could say even if it is his,
let's say I go ahead and I see his his well is
covered and I kick the cover off. Right? Presumably I'm liable. Okay,
but here's a case I put the cover on and then I
kick the cover off. Right, you could ask that question, right, forget
the stones. I decide to do a public service, I put a
cover on his well. Then I decide forget it, he did it
he dug it, let him be responsible, I take my cover back
off. Right, so whose well is it? Okay, so that's the first
more's question. We don't know. Yes.
It also plays into the question of extra טפח. tefakh.
Of extra yes the last טפח. tefakh טפח.
tefakh Right because the same way right that's why we're asking it
here because the last טפח tefakh I did an act and I've
totally made it mine. So how how much here even though the
first guy didn't nine tenths of the act, my act totally made
it mine when I dug that tenth. So that's the parallel, correct,
that's the right.
I didn't notice the parallel. I mean רש"י Rashi says טם טפח
וחזר וחפר בור עשרה או סמוך לעשרה וחזר אחריו וטם ומילא עפר
אותן טפח שהוסיף.
Tam tefakh v'chazar v'chafar bor asarah o samukh l'asarah
v'chazar acharav v'tam umilei afar otan tefakh shehosif.
Oh wait a minute I missed that רש"י. Rashi. He sees it
exactly as that case. טם טפח וחזר חפר בור עשרה או סמוך
לעשרה
וחזר אחריו וטם ומילא עפר אותן טפח שהוסיף.
Tam tefakh v'chazar chafur bor asarah o
samukh l'asarah v'chazar acharav v'tam umilei afar otan tefakh shehosif. Ah okay
you know what I had missed that רש"י Rashi so thank you.
Oh it's טם טפח tam tefakh he only did the one טפח.
tefakh Ah I was reading that as okay I appreciate that I
misread it so thank you Hillel corrects me. So I guess you
could ask my question but that's not the question being asked here
thank you Hillel. The question being asked here is that guy number
one did nine, guy number one did ten. Okay so this is
ראובן Reuven and this is שמעון. Shimon. Okay and then שמעון Shimon
after having added
one said let me go ahead and and fill that up. Right
so he filled up the טפח. tefakh And then and then he
removed it again right? No. וסילק אבניו. V'silek avnav. Oh no וסילק
אבניו v'silek avnav is back to that scenario. I'm sorry okay I'm
sorry I misinterpreted. Okay fine thank you. Okay thank you very much.
It's not what I said. What I said is a different question.
That's not this question. This question is I actually did reverse what
I did. Okay, I made it ten and now it's my בור.
And now I filled it up. Okay so I ממש mamash have
reversed my act and it's back to being nine. Okay, or I
added the stone and then I removed the stone. Okay how much
do we say well now we're back to just being ראובן's Reuven
בור. It looked exactly like it looked exactly before שמעון Shimon came
on the scene right? Which is I think the more natural thing
to say. Or do we say no you dug that it became
your בור now all you've done is you filled up one טפח
tefakh of your ten טפח tefakh בור. Okay so at least this
case by the way is more reasonable to see that you'd remain
חייב. When I put a stone outside the well to say and
then I remove it since it's all happening external to the well
it's hard to say in that case that I would remain חייב
if I reversed what I had done. But yes thank you I
apologize I totally misexplained this. Okay does everybody get this case now?
Okay it became mine and then I reversed what I did and
we're back to it being a nice more innocent nine טפח tefakh
thing. I made it ten by adding it and then I removed
it. Do we say okay it's my ten טפח tefakh well that
I now have that I just made nine טפח tefach or do
we say I'm out of the picture now? Okay thank you very
much let's read that again. בעי רבא טם טפח Bei Rava tam
tefakh if you filled in that last טפח tefach that you dug
או וסילק אבניו o v'silek avnav or you removed the stone that
you put at the edge of the well מהו? mahu? Okay מי
אמרינן מאי דעבד שקליה Mi amrinan mai de'avad shaklei או דלמא נסתלקו
מצרי ראשון o dilma nistalku matzrei rishon וקמלי כולה ברשותיה? v'kamli kulei
b'rishusei? Do we say we completely reversed what you did and it's
back to being שמעון's Shimon well? Or do we say that no
that it had completely become yours so you now ameliorated it somewhat
but it has it's now completely yours and you're still liable? תיקו
Teiku we don't know. Okay let's keep on going. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר שמואל בר מרתא. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar
Shmuel bar Marta. בור שמונה ומהן שני טפחים מים חייב. Bor shmonah
u'mehen shenei tefachim mayim chayav. If you have an eight טפח tefach
well I keep on saying well because well is with
water so here we actually finally are talking about well. If you
have an eight טפח tefach well with two טפחים the bottom two
טפחים of water you're חייב. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason?
כל טפח דמיא כתרי דייבשא דמי. Kol tefakh d'maya k'trei d'yavsha dami.
Because basically every טפח tefach of water is as injurious as two
טפחים of of an empty cavity. So you have six טפחים before
you hit the water and then two טפחים of water so that's
like an additional... four טפחים. So presumably we're not talking about הבלא,
havla, presumably we're talking about, I mean, about drowning, choking, or whatever.
It's not exact but anyway he says, that's as injurious as a
ten
טפח tefach בור.
Five טפחים and it was filled with water?
Yeah, I guess five טפחים all filled with water, right. Like
what we were talking about before, a baby can drown in an
inch of water.
Okay. רש״י touches
that too. רש״י says הבלא, havla, yeah, look at רש״י. מוסיף הבלא,
mosif havla, thank you. Yeah, I am constantly resisting talking about הבלא
havla as you noticed. Is it vapor?
I guess, maybe water vapor, I guess. Yeah.
That's the thinning of the air, it's the toxicity of the air.
Seems to be, I mean, yeah. Okay.
Okay, so גמרא says איבעיא להו: ibaya lehu: בור תשעה ומהן טפח
אחד מים מהו? bor tishah u-mehen tefach echad mayim mahu? How about
if it's nine and one, you know, חנן Chanan was asking just
five, let's say it was nine and one. So
מי אמרינן דכיון דלא נפישי מיא לית בהו הבלא? mi amrinan de-keivan
de-lo nefishei maya leit behu havla? Point, see I'm so resisting it.
או דלמא כיון דעמיק טפי אית ביה הבלא? o dilma keivan de-amik
tefei it beih havla? Okay, so do we say since there's only
one טפח tefach of water, one טפח tefach of water is not
enough to produce this extra הבלא, havla, so this two for one
power of water, you need a minimum amount of water, you need
two טפחים. One טפח tefach of water is not—does not produce more
punch, you know, than a normal טפח tefach of air, so it
would only be a nine טפח בור. Or do we say no,
one טפח of water is like two טפחים, even one טפח of
water is like two, and then it's a ten טפח בור. מי
אמרינן כיון דלא נפישי לית ביה הבלא או דלמא כיון דעמיק טפי?
mi amrinan keivan
de-lo nefishei leit beih havla o dilma keivan de-amik tefei? Or do
we say right, either there's not enough water to create הבלא, havla,
or do we say there's not enough water but there's greater depth.
It's nine, you know, it's nine with one of them as opposed
to eight with two of them. So because you start with greater
depth, אית ביה הבלא, it beih havla, there is הבלא havla even
with that one טפח of water. בור שבעה ומהן שלשה טפחים מים.
bor shivah u-mehen sheloshah tefachim mayim. Let's say you have seven of
which three is water, right? Are you getting this? It's basically right,
if you have the whole thing seven and then three of them
is water, what you really have is four of air and three
of water, so three times two becomes
six. Okay. What? No, it's like ten. If the whole thing is
seven but it's divided four and three, right, that's why I'm spelling
this out. It's not seven plus three. It's of them, so it's
four plus three. Okay, so do we
say מהו? mahu? Where are we? מי אמרינן כיון דנפישי מים טפי
אית ביה הבלא? mi amrinan keivan de-nefishei mayim tefei it beih havla?
With three טפחים of water you have even more הבלא, havla, so
of course it has the impact of six טפחים. או דלמא כיון
דלא עמיק כולי האי? o dilma keivan de-lo amik kuli hai? No,
or do we say because it only starts four טפחים down, it
doesn't start so deep down,
right, so לית ביה הבלא. leit beih havla. We don't know. So
this חידוש chiddush of eight, of like six plus two, there's a
question how far can we expand it, right? So can we expand
it to you know
this eight of two, can we expand it to nine and one,
seven and three, you know because the parameters change. Okay. בעי מיניה
רב שיזבי מרבא: bei minei Rav Shizbi me-Rava: הרחיבה מהו? hirchiva mahu?
So הרחיבה hirchiva goes ahead. חנן Chanan goes ahead and digs a
well and I figure I'm going to do a public service and
I'm going to open his well even more. Why is it a
public service? Because it decreases the הבלא. havla. Okay. So what do
we say? אמר
ליה הרי מיעט הבלא. amar leih harei miat havla. He decreased the
הבלא. havla. So people should give me a medal. אמר ליה: no,
אדרבה הרי קירב היזיקא. aderaba harei kireiv heizeika. You made it more
exposed for people falling in, right? You've increased the surface area that
somebody can fall into it. אלא אמר רב אשי נחזי אנן. ela
amar Rav Ashi nachzi anan. Let us look at it. אי בהבלא
מית הרי מיעט הבלא. ei be-havla mit harei miat havla. Let's see
how the guy died. If the guy died because out of some
asphyxiation or something that we can attribute to הבלא, havla, whatever that
is, then we'll say the second guy is פטור because he made
it less of a הבלא havla בור. אי בחבטא מית הרי קירב
היזיקא. ei be-chavta mit harei kireiv heizeika. If the guy died by
impact,
then the second guy is חייב. So איכא דאמרי, some say, אמר
רב אשי נחזי אנן. amar Rav Ashi nachzi anan. Let's look at
it. אי מהאי גיסא נפל הרי קירב היזיקא. ei me-hai gisa nafal
harei kireiv heizeika. If basically I—you fell into the part where I—the
part that I had expanded, right? If you fell into—if I expanded
on the north edge and you fell in on the north side,
then I'm then I'm liable. ואי מאידך גיסא נפל הרי מיעט הבלא.
ve-ei mi-idach gisa nafal harei miat havla. If you fell on the
south side, I've actually you know decreased the impact. Okay.
What's the understanding of נחזי אנן nachzi anan in this context? Like
we have a conceptual question, we're only going to see the effects
of the question and then determine the result.
I mean it's a good point that you're saying the נחזי אנן,
nachzi anan, you know נחזי אנן nachzi anan could be just used
as a phrase to say like you know well let's consider it
ourselves, but no, I think here it has a
really—I appreciate you stopping and pointing that out because I think here
the point is it's like wait a minute, this is not just
a theoretical question, this is going to be determined by what actually
happens in practice. Right. Until now we've been talking... Whose well is
it, whose whatever. It's like, you know what? This question is based
on like the גמרא before: did the animal fall in this way
or did it roll in? Like, you know, here the answer is
not, right, is not just an answer like A or B. It
depends on in practice what we see, what's going to happen.
And those previous questions were takers, those couldn't be determined by that.
Right, because it doesn't seem like those types of issues, like the
case about סימני מסירה Simanei Mesira and all those types of things...
Yeah, that's far more conceptual, right? I mean, this is also conceptual,
but a degree of it could be answered based on how the
events occur. Okay. איתמר: Itmar: בור שעמקו
כרחבו. Bor she-omko kerachvo. It's as deep as it is wide. רבה
ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו משמיה דרבה בר בר חנה דאמר משמיה דרבי
מני. Rabbah ve-Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu mishmeih d'Rabbah bar bar Channah d'amar
mishmeih d'Rabbi Mani.
חד אמר לעולם יש בו הבל עד שרחבו יתר על עמקו. Chad
amar l'olam yesh bo hevel ad she-rachvo yater al omko. It still
has הבל until it's wider than it's deep. So if it's exactly
the same, it still has הבל. וחד אמר לעולם אין בו הבל
עד שעמקו יתר על רחבו. Ve-chad amar l'olam ein bo hevel ad
she-omko yater al rachvo. No, it doesn't have הבל until it's deeper
than it is wide. So if it's exactly the same, it doesn't
have הבל. It's sort of like those אי אפשר לצמצם ee efshar
letzamtzem questions. Okay. איתמר... Itmar...
אבל... aval... Finally, after all that הבל stuff, which, as you see,
I have a hard time relating to, we're getting to this משנה
Mishnah about who's חייב. עבר
הראשון ולא כסהו. Avar harishon velo kishahu. First guy passed and didn't,
second guy passed and didn't, at least our version of the משנה
Mishnah says the second guy is חייב. So the גמרא says,
וראשון אימת מיפטר? Verishon eimat miptar? When does... at what stage, if
the second guy is חייב, what got the first guy off the
hook? That would be the way of reading it. Right, if you
have the רמב"ם's Rambam's גרסא, girsa, it says the first guy is
חייב, and then the question is what does the first guy have
to do to get off the hook? Okay, but we'll read it
רש"י. Rashi. The second guy is חייב. What got the first guy
off the hook? What occurred that the first guy's off the hook?
רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו משמיה דרבה בר בר חנה דאמר משמיה
דרבי מני. Rabbah ve-Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu mishmeih d'Rabbah bar bar Channah
d'amar mishmeih d'Rabbi Mani. חד אמר משמניחו משתמש, Chad amar mishemenicho mishtamesh,
that the second... that the first guy was there at the well,
the second guy came over and then started using the well. So
because I see you're using the well, goodbye. So the fact that
the second guy was using it and only at that stage the
first guy left, there's an implicit handing off of responsibility. וחד אמר
משימסור לו דליו, Ve-chad amar misheyimsor lo dalyo, that actually the first
guy has to give him the... you know, the cover of the
well. Says, okay, I uncovered the well to go take some water,
you number two showed up, I'm going to go here, here, take
the cover. Okay, so that's a radically different than the גמרא, you
know, sort of describes. The גמרא describes like the first guy just
walked by and ignored it and then the second guy walked by
and ignored it. The גמרא says no, actually they were using it
and what got the first guy off the hook was that there
was some implicit or explicit handing over of responsibility to the second
guy. Okay.
And then you want to know if none of that happened, what
would be the הלכה? Would they both be equally חייב, right, you
know? So that's not spelled out. Okay. כתנאי. Ke-tannai. Let's say this
is like a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. הממלא מים מן הבור ובא
חבירו ואמר לו הנח לי ואני אדלה מים. Hamemalei mayim min habor
u-ba chaveiro ve-amar lo hanach li va-ani edleh mayim. So one guy
was drawing water and the other guy said, you know what, leave
it to me I'll draw the water now. Okay, maybe they were
both trying to irrigate a shared field or something like that. כיון
שהניחו משתמש פטור. Keivan she-henicho mishtamesh patur. When the first guy left
the second guy to go draw, he's exempt. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
אומר משימסור לו דליו. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer misheyimsor lo dalyo.
Now literally the דלי really means the bucket, but רש"י Rashi interprets
דליו dalyo with כיסוי הבור. kisui habor. Okay, so... so I don't
know exactly. Anyway. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? What's the debate? רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב סבר יש ברירה. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov savar yesh breira.
There is ברירה. breira. Right, ברירה breira is like after something happens
retroactively you sort of say that it all sort of was the
way it was
going to happen. So האי מדידיה קממלא והאי מדידיה קממלא. Hai mideidieh
kamemalei ve-hai mideidieh kamemalei. Okay, so that at the end of the
day, you know what, let's stop here because it's already 8:30 and
I don't want to... it's going to be a little confusing. Okay,
so we will pick up with this ברירה breira question and this
shared responsibility with the בור tomorrow.